Guide to the George MacDonald Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1831-1946; Series I; 5.25; (13 boxes)
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters to George MacDonald and Family
      - Gurney, Ellen (Emilia), 1860-95, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77-78)
      - "H" general, 1889-90 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - Helps, Arthur, 1870 Apr 5 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Hill, Octavia Hill, Emily, 1869-1910 (Box 2, Folder 81-82)
      - Holland, Annie E. (Mrs. J. G. Holland), 1873 Feb 16 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1873 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - Howard, G., 1881, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
      - Hughes, Arthur, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      - Hughes, Edward, 1874-78 (Box 2, Folder 86a)
      - Hughes, Thomas, 1865 Aug 27 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      - "I" general, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 88)
      - Irving, Edward, 1831 Feb 24 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - Jowett, Benjamin, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - "K" general, 1870-87 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - Kingsley, Charles, 1865-74 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      - "L" general, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      - Lawless, Emily, 1883 Apr 17 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - Leigh-Smith, Anna, 1877, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Lewes, Gertrude (with note from Louisa MacDonald), 1874 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Lewis, Kate (Terry), 1872, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Lynch, Thomas, 1851-53 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Lyttleton, Edith (?), 1884-93 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Lyttleton, Laura
      - "M" general, 1853-74 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - MacColl, [Eliza?], 1868-90 (Box 2, Folder 101)
        MacColl's letters date from 1868-1869. Accompanied by letter (1890) from Alice Jackson, niece and adopted daughter of Eliza MacColl.
      - Macgregor, Creror D., 1873 (Box 2, Folder 102)
      - Martin, Frances, 1865-79 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      - Masson, David, 1865 Aug 14 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      - Matheson, W. J., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 105)
      - Matthews, Elizabeth, 1872 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      - Maurice, F. D., 1862-72 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      - Morris, Caleb, 1852 Oct 30 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      - Morris, Jane, 1892 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 109)
      - Mount-Temple, Georgina, Lady (Cowper), 1869-79 (Box 2, Folder 110)
      - Munro, Alex, 1858, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 111)
      - Munro, Annie, 1874, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 112)
      - Nennes, M., 1853 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 113)
      - Oakey, Maria (Dewing), 1873-74 (Box 2, Folder 114)
      - Oliphant, Margaret, 1884-92, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 115)
      - Plumptre, Edward Hayes, 1865-66 (Box 2, Folder 116)
      - Pym, Eva Pym, Alexander, 1887-88, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 117)
      - "R" general, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 118)
      - Ralston, W., 1867, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 119)
      - Reid, George, 1868-78 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      - Rennie, James, 1868 Sep 15 (Box 3, Folder 121)
      - Rhys, Ernest, 1882 Jan 24 (Box 3, Folder 122)
      - Robertson, Forbes, 1863? Jan 31 (Box 3, Folder 123)
      - Robinson, Henry Crabb, 1859, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 124)
      - Rolleston, George, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - Ross, A. J., 1851-57 (Box 3, Folder 126)
      - Ruskin, John, 1865 Aug 18 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      - Russell, E. F., 1882, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 128)
      - "S" general, 1864-1906 (Box 3, Folder 129)
        Contains a letter from Frederic Shields to "Miss Cavendish Bentnick."
      - Scott, A. J. (Alexander John) and Ann, 1852-62, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 130)
      - Scott-Siddons, Mary F., 1873 May 4 (Box 3, Folder 131)
      - Smith, George C., 1848 Feb 25 (Box 3, Folder 132)
      - Spence, Ralph Spence, Robert, 1848-58 (Box 3, Folder 133)
      - Strahan, Alexander, 1869-73 (Box 3, Folder 134)
      - Sutton, Henry, 1856-99 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      - "T" general, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - Thomson, Courlaide (?) Thomson, Winifred Hope, 1883-84 (Box 3, Folder 137)
      - Tompkins, Mary Ellen, 1845, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 138)
      - Twain, Mark
        See: Samuel L. Clemens, Box 1, folder 57
      - "V-W" general, 1871-87 (Box 3, Folder 139)
      - Wells, A., 1850 Jun 18 (Box 3, Folder 140)
      - Whitney, Adeline D. T., 1873, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 141)
      - Wright, William Burnet, 1894-96 (Box 3, Folder 142)
      - Yarnell, Agnes, 1876, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 143)
      - Unidentified, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from George MacDonald
      - Correspondence, 1830-39 (Box 3, Folder 145)
      - Correspondence, 1840-49 (Box 3, Folder 146-48)
      - Correspondence, 1850-59 (Box 3, Folder 149-59)
      - Correspondence, 1860-69 (Box 3, Folder 160-61)
      - Correspondence, 1870-79 (Box 4, Folder 162-64)
      - Correspondence, 1880-89 (Box 4, Folder 165-68)
      - Correspondence, 1890-99, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 169-77)
      - Letter album. Copies of letters from George MacDonald to family and friends (1846-1890, with notes on Sunday services at Casa Coraggio) (Box 4, Folder 178)
    - Letters to George MacDonald
      - Correspondence, 1848-49 (Box 5, Folder 179-85)
      - Correspondence, 1850 (Box 5, Folder 186-91)
      - Correspondence, 1851 (Box 5, Folder 192-94)
      - Correspondence, 1852 (Box 5, Folder 195)
      - Correspondence, 1853 (Box 5, Folder 196-97)
      - Correspondence, 1854 (Box 6, Folder 198)
      - Correspondence, 1855 (Box 6, Folder 199-200)
      - Correspondence, 1856-58 (Box 6, Folder 201)
      - Correspondence, 1861-65 (Box 6, Folder 202)
      - Correspondence, 1866-67 (Box 6, Folder 203)
      - Correspondence, 1868 (Box 6, Folder 204)
      - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 6, Folder 205)
      - Correspondence, 1870 (Box 6, Folder 206)
      - Correspondence, 1871-79 (Box 6, Folder 207)
      - Correspondence, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 208)
      - Correspondence, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 209)
      - Correspondence, 1891-95 (Box 6, Folder 210)
    - Other MacDonald Family Letters
      - Correspondence, 1830-39 (Box 7, Folder 211-12)
      - Correspondence, 1840-49 (Box 7, Folder 213-19)
      - Correspondence, 1850-59 (Box 7, Folder 220-34)
      - Correspondence, 1860-69 (Box 7, Folder 235-43)
      - Correspondence, 1860-69 (Box 8, Folder 244-58)
      - Correspondence, 1870-79 (Box 8, Folder 259-64)
      - Correspondence, 1870-79 (Box 9, Folder 265-86)
      - Correspondence, 1870-79 (Box 10, Folder 287-305)
      - Correspondence, 1870-79 (Box 11, Folder 306-18)
      - Correspondence, 1880-89 (Box 11, Folder 319-28)
      - Correspondence, 1880-89 (Box 12, Folder 329-45)
      - Correspondence, 1890-99 (Box 12, Folder 346-56)
      - Correspondence, 1890-99 (Box 13, Folder 357-65)
      - Correspondence, 1900-09 (Box 13, Folder 366-71)
      - Correspondence, 1910-19 (Box 13, Folder 372-75)
      - Correspondence, 1920-29 (Box 13, Folder 376-79)
      - Correspondence, 1930-39 (Box 13, Folder 380-81)
      - Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 382-83)
      - "Letters from America" (letters from Louisa MacDonald to her children [1872 Sep-Nov], copied by Lilia Scott Macdonald, with synopses of letters by Winifred Macdonald at end) (Box 13, Folder 384)
      - "Notes Referring to the Family Letters, 1833-1905" (notes by Winifred L. MacDonald, genealogy, photos), 1946 (Box 13, Folder 385)
- Writings, 1847-1925; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings consists of a number of poems (holograph and copies) by George MacDonald, an adaptation of Pilgrim's Progress by Louisa MacDonald, and juvenile writings and sketches by his children.
  - Writings of George MacDonald
    - "Big White Lily", 1877 Jan 4 (Box 14, Folder 386)
    - "Christmas, 1879" (Box 14, Folder 387)
    - "Ever on Earth to Be" (unestablished (Box 14, Folder 388)
      - authorship), n.d.
    - "January 4, 1879" (Box 14, Folder 389)
    - Lilith: poster advertisement
      See: Oversize, Box 17, folder 485
    - "A Marriage Offering" ("Wedding Song"), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 390)
    - "The New Year" (copy), 1886 Dec 31 (Box 14, Folder 391)
    - "New Year, 1878" (Box 14, Folder 392)
    - "Novalis' Spiritual Songs" (translation, incomplete), [c. 1851] (Box 14, Folder 393)
    - "An Old Story" (copy), 1886 (Box 14, Folder 394)
    - ["Time Dieth Ever"], 1847 Jan (Box 14, Folder 395)
    - "To L. S. M. D." [Lilia Scott MacDonald], [1880?] (Box 14, Folder 396)
    - "To My Elfie" (copy by E. R. Hughes), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 397)
  - Writings of Louisa MacDonald
    - "Dramatic Illustrations from John Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress " in the Year 1877, arranged by Mrs. George MacDonald.": printed text, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 398)
  - Juvenile Works of MacDonald Children
    - Lilia Scott Macdonald: untitled juvenile story (with letter by Greville MacDonald), 1869 (Box 14, Folder 399)
    - Juvenile poems and sketches, 1873, 1885, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 400)
    - Juvenile fiction (Mary Josephine and Grace MacDonald?) (Box 14, Folder 401)
    - "The Hastings Gazette", 1873 (Box 14, Folder 402)
    - "The Reculver Magazine", 1870 (Box 14, Folder 403)
    - "The Reculver Record", 1871 (Box 14, Folder 404)
  - Writings of Others
    - "Rhymes on the Waist of Louisa Powell, by Her Sisters", 1850 May 27 (Box 14, Folder 405)
- Family Papers, 1822-88; Series III; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Family Papers, consists of diaries, photographs, news clippings, documents, printed material and other memorabilia related to the family of George MacDonald.
  - Calling cards
    - George and Louisa MacDonald (Box 15, Folder 406)
    - Visitors' cards, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 407)
  - Diaries
    - Caroline Grace MacDonald, 1870 (Box 15, Folder 408)
    - Lilia Scott MacDonald, 1865, 1872 (Box 15, Folder 409-10)
    - Louisa MacDonald, 1856-85 (Box 15, Folder 411)
  - MacDonald, George, Sr.: death notices, 1858 (Box 15, Folder 412)
  - MacDonald, George
    - Congregational Church at Arundel: George MacDonald's offer of resignation, [1852?] (Box 15, Folder 413)
    - King's College and University, Aberdeen: admittance cards for classes, 1840-44 (Box 15, Folder 414)
    - Lecture announcements and testimonials (American tour), 1873 (Box 15, Folder 415)
    - Signatures, 1866, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 416)
  - MacDonald, Greville M.: "Testimonials to Mr. G. M. MacDonald, M. R. C. S.", [1879] (Box 15, Folder 417)
  - MacDonald, Louisa
    - Birth certificate, 1822 (Box 15, Folder 418)
    - Permission to travel on the continent, 1877 (Box 15, Folder 419)
  - MacDonald family mementoes
    - Cloth satchel (stencilled "1874") (Box 15, Folder 420)
    - Monogram from handkerchief of Phoebe Powell, mother of Louisa Powell MacDonald (Box 15, Folder 421)
    - Pressed flowers, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 422)
  - Newspaper clippings (extracts from American newspapers), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 423-24)
  - Photographs and sketches
    - MacDonald family album, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 425)
    - MacDonald, George, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 426)
    - MacDonald, George MacKay (?), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 427)
    - MacDonald, Louisa, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 428)
    - MacDonald, Robert Falconer, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 429)
    - Others (non-family), n.d. (Box 16, Folder 430)
    - Scenes from Pilgrim's Progress, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 431)
    - Casa Coraggio, [c. 1887] (Box 16, Folder 432)
    - MacDonald gravesites, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 433)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 434)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 435)
  - Printed material
    - "Amateur Concert for the Church Building Fund" (Bordighera): printed program and words to songs, 1883 (Box 16, Folder 436)
    - "Blue Beard" ("Performed in the garden of the Retreat on June 8th or 9th, 1872"): printed text (Box 16, Folder 437)
    - Menu card (National Liberal Club: with signatures of George MacDonald, Bret Harte, Wilkie Collins, and others), 1888 Jun 18 (Box 16, Folder 438)
    - "Table songs" (printed musical score), 1886 (Box 16, Folder 439)
    - "Grace After Meat" (printed prayer), n.d.
  - Writings of others
    - Fosdick, Mary. Untitled poem: holograph, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 440)
    - Gilder, Richard Watson. "Palazzo Cattaneo": holograph, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 441)
    - ["Oh, Mother of thy Son: what name will Fall"]: holograph copy, [1879]
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 442)
- Additions Since 1998, 1856-1886; Series IV; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  - GEORGE J. LEON GIFT
    Gift of George J. Leon, 1950
    - Correspondence
      - Cole, Nina
        - ALS to Louisa Powell MacDonald, announcing the death of Rose La Touche. [London], 4 p., [1875] May 26 (Box 17, Folder 443)
          Includes: ANS from Mrs. M. C. Bishop of the same date, and typescript copy of the note
      - La Touche, Maria Price
        - 8 ALS to George MacDonald. Harristown, Ireland, 1863, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 444-6)
          Includes: Typescript copy of the first letter and last two
        - ALS to Lilia Scott MacDonald. [Harristown, Ireland], 7 p., [1867 Jan 24] (Box 17, Folder 447)
          Includes: Typescript copy
        - 13 ALS to Louisa Powell MacDonald. Various places, 1865-68, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 448-51)
          Includes: Typescript copies of six of the letters, and an envelope postmarked July 14, 1867
          Excerpts from some of the letters are printed in Derrick Leon's Ruskin: The Great Victorian, London, 1949
      - La Touche, Rose
        - 5 ALS to George MacDonald. Various places, 1872 (Box 17, Folder 452-53)
          Includes: Typescript copy of letter of June 18, 1872
        - 13 ALS to Louisa Powell MacDonald. Various places, 1872-74 (Box 17, Folder 454-56)
          Includes: Typescript copies of many of the letters, as well as typescript copy of a letter dated Nov. 10, [1972-3?], for which the original is not present
        - AL to John Ruskin. [Tunbridge Wells], 8 p. with envelope, 1872 Jun 19 (Box 17, Folder 457)
          Originally enclosed in a letter to George MacDonald, of the same date, from which it has been removed. "This letter...was never given to Ruskin..." says Derrick Leon in his Ruskin: The Great Victorian, London, 1949, p. 488
          Includes: [Grenville MacDonald's?] notes concerning the letter, and by a typescript copy of the letter
      - MacDonald, George
        - ALS to John Ruskin. Guildford, 5 p., 1875 May 30 (Box 18, Folder 458)
        - Telegram to John Ruskin. London, [1872? Jul] (Box 18, Folder 459)
          Includes: Typescript copy and a message from the Post Office in London, dated Jul. 14, 1872, reporting non-delivery of another telegram to Ruskin
      - MacDonald, Louisa Powell
        - ALS to Maria Price La Touche. Hammersmith, 4 p., [1868] Jul 2 (Box 18, Folder 460)
      - Mount-Temple, Georgina Cowper-Temple
        - Telegram to George MacDonald concerning John Ruskin, [London], 1872 Jul 17 (Box 18, Folder 461)
      - Ruskin, John
        - 65 ALS and 5 telegrams to George MacDonald, many of them concerning Rose La Touche, 1863-86, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 462-78)
          Includes: 57 typescript copies and notes about several of the letters written in the hand of [Grenville MacDonald?]
        - 7 ALS to Louisa Powell MacDonald, London and Oxford, 1865-75, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 479-80)
          Includes: typescript copies of all except the letter of 1875
          Letter of [April 10, 1866] includes envelope addressed to George MacDonald, dated June 2, 1863; a note in [Grenville MacDonald's?] hand concerning the envelope; and Ruskin's autograph clipped from another letter
        - 2 ALS to Lilia Scott MacDonald, [London], 1866 (Box 18, Folder 481)
          Includes: Typescript copies
      - Severn, Joan
        - ALS to George MacDonald about John Ruskin. Coniston, 3 p., [1878] Mar 4 (Box 18, Folder 482)
          Printed in part in Derrick Leon's Ruskin: The Great Victorian, p. 510
    - Other Papers
      - La Touche, Maria Price. "Scenes by Dreamlight", holograph manuscript poem of 77 stanzas, 27 p., 1856 Mar (Box 18, Folder 483)
      - La Touche, Rose [supposed author]. "Isaiah - LVIII - 10", holograph poem of four stanzas, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 484)
        Begins "I went to look for Jesus", written in the hand of her mother, Maria Price La Touche, 2 p. Removed from Mrs. La Touche's letter to Mrs. George MacDonald, March 14, 1868
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Publicity poster for Lilith, n.d. (Box bsd, folder 485)